<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://www.strika.info' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<title>
Nebojša Stričević
</title>
<link>
http://www.strika.info
</link>
<description>
Strika's personal website.
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Fri, 13 May 2016 16:04:29 +0000
</lastBuildDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-05-13-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-05-13-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;This week I completed last formal steps for joining Toptal and I'm now a Toptal member. Still didn't spend much time on the platform, searching for jobs, as I'm busy with client work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href='/papers.html'&gt;Organizing Programs Without Classes&lt;/a&gt; which compares class based object oriented languages with those based on prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued working on a side project - managing book collections for teams, but I still struggle at finding time for it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 13 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-05-06-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-05-06-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I continued working on the client project that I started the last week. I learned that the project started as a pre-Rails 1.0 application. It's great to work on an application that's been ticking for so long.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the start of the week I worked intensively on my Toptal application. Yesterday, I had the last interview and I'm now accepted to Toptal talent pool. I'm still not sure how much work will I do through Toptal, but it's nice to have that as an option.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week I read &lt;a href='/papers.html'&gt;Searching for Spaceships&lt;/a&gt; by David Eppstein. Although it's not written for the wide programming community, it's very interesting if you're into &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The&amp;#95;Game&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;Life'&gt;Life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 06 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-29-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-29-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt; I focused most of my time on a new client project, that will probably keep me  busy for the next few months. It's an established project that's been around  for around 10 years. It has a small, but dedicated team. So far, I spent most  of my time learning about the domain and the code base, but I also did few  smaller contributions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I read Donald Knuth's ACM Turing award lecture from 1974 - Computer Programming  as an Art. Read more about it on the &lt;a href='/papers.html'&gt;list of papers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; I learned few surprising (to me) but useful tips related to Ruby on Rails and  testing this week. I created &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/rails-tips'&gt;Rails Tips&lt;/a&gt;  repository to collect them. I choose a GitHub repository, as I welcome  contributions. I'm generally looking for tips related to Ruby or Rails or  related tools that are less known, interesting or surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 29 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-22-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-22-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I worked on a client project and I found another project that will keep my busy for the next few months. If you still want to work with me, please contact me to check my availability. I might still be open for smaller consulting gigs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had another Toptal interview that I passed. And I have one more step left before I can join Toptal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week I choose to read &lt;em&gt;Why Functional Programming Matters&lt;/em&gt; by John Hughes. The paper was published in 1984. It discusses advantages of functional programming over &quot;conventional&quot; languages.  In particular, it discusses how higher order functions and lazy evaluation contribute to modularity. I also printed out several papers for the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I switched to &lt;a href='https://neovim.io/'&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; as my main editor instead of Vim. Few fellow developers reported that it's stable enough for daily use. I'll try it out for the next few weeks. I created a new GitHub repository for &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/neovimfiles'&gt;Neovim configuration&lt;/a&gt; and updated my &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/dotfiles'&gt;dotfiles repository&lt;/a&gt; to install Neovim automatically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the next few weeks, I plan to focus on client projects and to wrap up Toptal application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-15-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-15-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;This week, I concentrated on Toptal application. I continued going through &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/codility'&gt;Codility lessons&lt;/a&gt;. Although I didn't complete all lessons, I concluded that I did enough to officially apply at Toptal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had my first Toptal screening interview on Thursday. It was a short, pleasant conversation and the Toptal person informed me that I can continue to Codility based test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did Codility test on Friday. I'm still waiting for results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I helped &lt;a href='http://hackberry.co'&gt;Tanja&lt;/a&gt; complete some old projects. It was a sort of spring cleaning for freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also did some paperwork and learned more about running a business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-08-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-08-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I continued working on the client project. And I did a smaller job to help out &lt;a href='http://hackberry.co'&gt;Tanja&lt;/a&gt; with her work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I fixed 2 annoying exceptions for &lt;a href='http://servisne.info'&gt;servisne.info&lt;/a&gt;, the service I developed and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read The Humble Programmer, the ACM Turing award Lecture by &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edsger&amp;#95;W.&amp;#95;Dijkstra'&gt;Dijkstra&lt;/a&gt; from 1972. And it's a fantastic paper! I wrote more about that on &lt;a href='/papers.html'&gt;the papers list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also continued working on &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/codility'&gt;Codility lessons&lt;/a&gt;. It's interesting that another programmer contacted me though the repository. We exchanged few emails with tips and shared our experience about Codility and programming in general.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-01-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-04-01-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I started working on a client project. However, I still have one slot left. If you need my help, or if you know someone who might, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a new laptop - Macbook Pro 13&quot;. My initial choice was Dell XPS 13&quot; with Ubuntu. The main problem with Dell + Ubuntu is that some popular software (like Skype) doesn't work great. A friend advised me that this is something potential clients don't want to hear about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm used to working on 27&quot; iMac and didn't expect much from Macbook Pro. But, it's a really nice machine. It's good looking, faster than iMac and it has a great screen. My only criticism is that the keyboard is not that great. It has that clickety sound, like I have long finger nails. But, it's not a big problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I visited a local meetup that featured 2 talks. The first one was by Sandra Prvulović, an HR expert. It discussed the problem of finding experienced developers for a company. One of the most interesting remarks I heard is that the IT companies have more or less equal offer in Novi Sad. Because of that, not many developers switch companies, although many say that they would if a company makes a good offer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other talk was by &lt;a href='https://medium.com/@tijanamomirov'&gt;Tijana Momirov&lt;/a&gt;. She talked about her experience living and working as a digital nomad. It was a very inspiring talk for someone who's just starting his own business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read the paper &lt;a href='https://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/dat/tfp12/tfp12.pdf'&gt;Some History of Functional Programming Languages&lt;/a&gt; by D. A. Turner. It was generally an interesting paper, although hard to follow in some parts. I did learn some interesting facts, though. For example, that &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp&amp;#95;%28programming&amp;#95;language%29'&gt;LISP&lt;/a&gt;, was not influenced by &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambda&amp;#95;calculus'&gt;lambda calculus&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently, &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John&amp;#95;McCarthy&amp;#95;%28computer&amp;#95;scientist%29'&gt;John McCarthy&lt;/a&gt; didn't study &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonzo&amp;#95;Church'&gt;Church's&lt;/a&gt; papers, before he invented LISP. Modern lisps, however, are based on lambda calculus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another interesting part is a discussion about languages that influenced &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haskell&amp;#95;%28programming&amp;#95;language%29'&gt;Haskell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My plan is to continue reading one &lt;a href='/papers.html'&gt;paper every week&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also continued working on &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/codility'&gt;Codility lessons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-03-25-log.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-03-25-log.html
</link>
<title>
Log
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;This was my first week as an independent consultant. And it went pretty slow. A project that I planned for this week got postponed, so I concentrated on some preparation work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I updated my homepage a little bit. The website needs a full redesign, but for now, my goal was to make it decent. I updated the text on the homepage, added some links to the articles I wrote and the link to the &lt;a href='http://video.webcamp.si/wc2016&amp;#95;stricevic&amp;#95;supercharged&amp;#95;feature&amp;#95;flags/'&gt;conference talk&lt;/a&gt; I recently gave at WebCamp.si. I also started writing a short summary of my professional life, to replace the CV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another thing that I set up is this log of my weekly activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did some research about Toptal as a source of clients. To get into Toptal, you need to pass a interview process, much like a standard company interview. One of the tasks is &lt;a href='https://codility.com/'&gt;Codility&lt;/a&gt; test. I tried doing few Codility tests that are &lt;a href='https://codility.com/programmers/lessons/'&gt;freely available&lt;/a&gt; and they are harder than I though. So I set up a &lt;a href='https://github.com/strika/codility'&gt;git repository&lt;/a&gt; and started going through the lessons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My goal is to complete as many lessons as I can. I learned few things so far:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lessons are harder than I thought. I'm not as good as I though.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I can get better by practicing. Ideas can be applied in different  challenges.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You need to know what &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big&amp;#95;O&amp;#95;notation'&gt;Big O notation&lt;/a&gt; is.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Every task in Codility has expectations for performance expressed in Bit O  notation. This is also a hint and a guide how you need to implement the solution.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's good to write code that generates test data and to use benchmarking to  make sure a solution has good performance.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's useful to develop a naive or slow solution first (if you can do that  fast), as you can use it to test the fast solution, that often has more  complex implementation.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My solutions to more complex problems are not that readable and the code is  not great.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I plan to continue working on Codility challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also migrated email sending for a side project that I have (&lt;a href='http://servisne.info'&gt;servisne.info&lt;/a&gt;) from Mandrill to Mailgun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 25 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-03-21-hello-world.html
</guid>
<link>
http://www.strika.info/posts/2016-03-21-hello-world.html
</link>
<title>
Hello World
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Today is my first day as an independent consultant. For the last 4 years I worked on &lt;a href='https://semaphoreci.com'&gt;Semaphore&lt;/a&gt;, a continuous integration service used daily by thousands of developers around the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, I decided to join my wife &lt;a href='http://hackberry.co'&gt;Tanja&lt;/a&gt; and to find a niche where we can make a difference. We're still working on that. Until then, I'll work as an independent consultant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I plan to use this page as the log of my weekly activities. I'm still not sure if this is a good idea - to make this page public, but I'll still try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Mon, 21 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000
</pubDate>
<author>
Nebojša Stričević
</author>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
